Okay, next section deals with the restrictive diseases.
Now, I realize that this can be a particularly difficult topic,
or quote-unquote a difficult topic,
and medical students are a little bit wary of this topic
because it's sort of hyped up to be particularly difficult.
But I actually don't think that this section is that hard,
and I'm hopeful that you'll agree with me
by the time we reach the end of the section.
So the first principle that you have to keep in mind
is that in a restrictive disease,
you're restricted from filling the lung.
There's a problem with the ability to fill the lung.
Now, remember that in an obstructive disease,
the problem was the ability to empty the lung.
In a restrictive disease, the problem is the ability to fill the lung.
If you can't fill the lung,
obviously the total lung capacity is going to go down.
If you can't bring air into the lung,
the total lung capacity measures how much air
you can actually hold in the lung.
And if you can't put air in the lung,
obviously the total lung capacity will be down.
In addition, the forced vital capacity will be down.
The forced vital capacity is the amount of air
that you can blow out after breathing in all the way.
So you take a very deep breath
and blow out as much as you can.
That's the forced vital capacity.
And that will be down
because if you can't bring air into the lung,
you're going to have a problem.
You're not going to be able to get that much air out, right?
So that you can't fill it,
so therefore there'll be less coming out.
So the forced vital capacity will be down.
The forced expiratory volume over a one-second period,
the FEV1, will also be down.
And that, again, is the amount of air
that comes out in the first second
after you breathe all the way in and then blow out.
So when you're blowing out that very first second,
that's the amount of air that comes out in that first second.
And if you can't fill the lung,
you're not going to be able to get as much air out
in that first second period.
What's important to note, however,
is that this ratio,
again, both the FEV1 and the FVC are going down,
but the ratio actually increases.
Now, what do I mean by that?
Let's go back to normal for a minute.
Remember that the normal forced expiratory volume
over a one-second period is four liters.
So that when I breathe in all the way and I blow out,
in the first second, I'm going to blow out about four liters.
And the total amount that I can blow out,
the forced vital capacity, would be about five liters.
So otherwise stated, normally about 80% of the air
is blown out in the first second.
Now, what happens in a restrictive disease
is that my forced vital capacity,
the amount of air that I can blow out totally,
would go down.
So for example, let's say that that goes down to four liters.
And my forced expiratory volume,
the amount that's going to come out in that first second,
is also going to go down,
but it's not going to go down as much relative to normal.
So that maybe it becomes 3.5.
So when, you know, 3.5 over four is like greater than 85%.
So this becomes greater than 80%.
And that's important because that's one of the classic hallmarks
of this particular, these particular disorders.
And it's pretty easy to remember
because basically that forced expiratory volume over one second,
what increases it is the fact that when you get a restrictive disease,
you often have a lot of fibrosis in the lung.
And that fibrosis in the lung increases the elastic recoil of the lung.
And that increase in elastic recoil is going to allow you
to be able to squeeze air out more quickly
over that first one second period.
And so that's one way to think about it.
Another way to think about it is when you get all that fibrosis,
you're not going to get collapse of any of the airways.
And as you don't get collapse of the airways,
then the air is going to be able to rush out of the lung more quickly.
Because the acceleration of the air does cause some compression
or collapsing inward of the airways.
But that's not going to happen because the fibrosis
is going to trap all those airways open.
So that's another way to think about it.
Regardless, you do need to know that that ratio is increased.
And remember that in the obstructive disorders,
the ratio was decreased.
And again, that was the hallmark of those obstructive disorders
that we've already covered.
You can go back and review that if that wasn't clear.
Most commonly, the restrictive diseases
are going to be due to something called
an interstitial disease of the lung.
Now, what are interstitial diseases of the lung?
These are disorders in which you get fibrosis of the interstitium.
And what's the interstitium?
Well, if you go back and recall,
remember that you've got these alveolar air sacs
down in the exchange portion of the lung.
And the wall of these alveolar air sacs
is super delicate and thin.
Now, the reason you want that to be super delicate and thin
is because you're going to exchange oxygen and carbon dioxide
across that barrier.
So you want a super thin barrier.
In an interstitial fibrosing process,
you get fibrosis of the interstitium.
And it's fibrosis of the interstitium
that thickens that barrier.
And the thickening of the barrier
then is going to prohibit the ability
to exchange gases very well.
That's going to be one problem.
But another problem is you're not going to be able
to fill that lung because it's going to be hard
to open that fibrosis when you want to fill this airway.
And so there's going to be a problem.
There's going to be a restrictive problem,
an inability to properly fill the lung.
So that's the most common cause of restrictive disease,
interstitial fibrosis.
Now, another way by which we can have
a restricted filling of the lung
is by having an abnormality of the chest wall.
For example, let's say the patient's obese, right?
So as the patient is trying to fill the lung,
they've got to blow open that chest wall.
They've got to fight the force of the chest
in order to open the lung completely.
And so if there is a lot of force in the chest wall,
for example, due to obesity,
that force in the chest wall is going to prohibit the lung
from being able to open and fill as much.
And so that would also result in a restrictive disease.
Now, the first of these disorders
is called idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis.
And the key disorder here
is that you get fibrosis of the lung interstitium.
All right, idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis
where you get fibrosis of the lung interstitium.
This is what it classically looks like.
And you can see here,
this is probably as close to normal
as we have on this slide.
This is the normal alveolar air sac.
And you can see that the wall of the alveolar sac
is very thin and delicate.
Now, notice here,
you've got another alveolar air sac here,
but this wall is way too thick.
This interstitium has become fibrosed.
Here, you can see how much fibrosis
there is in the interstitium.
And so that's classic for this disorder
called idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis.
Now, in this particular disorder,
what happens is you get cyclical lung injury.
And nobody knows why,
hence the term idiopathic.
But our current understanding is that
with this cyclical lung injury,
you get cyclical healing.
And remember that one of the key mediators of healing
is TGF-beta.
If you go back and recall
from your lectures in inflammation,
I mentioned during inflammation
that when the macrophages come in,
the macrophages can do different things.
Like they can create additional acute inflammation
by secreting IL-8.
They can induce fibrosis.
They can call in the healing response.
And at that point,
I told you that there were two important mediators
that allow for calling in of the healing response.
And one was TGF-beta,
and the other one was IL-10.
And so in this particular case,
you can see that TGF-beta is important
for the healing response.
And so the injured pneumocytes
can also release TGF-beta,
and that would induce fibrosis.
And that is what is thought to drive the process.
It's TGF-beta from the injured pneumocytes
that induces the fibrosis.
That's important to know.
Now remember,
when a patient has this kind of interstitial fibrosis,
you have to first exclude other causes.
So for example,
you have to make sure
that it's not due to some drugs,
like bleomycin is a high-yield example,
or amiodarum is another high-yield example.
You've got to exclude radiation therapy,
which can also cause an interstitial fibrosis.
And you've got to exclude other causes as well.
And once you've excluded all the other causes,
then you would call it idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis.
Now clinically,
these patients are going to have shortness of breath
that's going to get worse over time.
And it gets worse over time
because the fibrosis progresses over time.
At the same time,
they're going to have cough.
If a lung CT was performed,
you would see fibrosis on that lung CT.
Very important to know
is that the fibrosis initially begins
in the sub-pleural regions,
right underneath the pleural of the lung.
And eventually, over time,
it can progress to involve the entire lung.
When it involves the entire lung
and there's diffuse fibrosis throughout the lung,
that's called honeycomb lung.
Now there's no way to remove this fibrosis
and so the treatment is lung transplantation.
And that's because we have no way of removing the fibrosis.
Another disorder that could result in interstitial fibrosis
is called the pneumoconiosis.
Pneumoconiosis are basically disorders
in which you get fibrosis
due to some occupational exposure
that then activates the macrophages
to lay down fibrosis.
Let's start with small particles.
Now the notion is that if you've got big particles
present in the environment,
when you breathe in,
the mucus and the cilia, etc.,
will actually filter those big particles.
So these have to be particles
that are small enough
that can get to the very bottom exchange
or distal exchange portion of the lung,
which will then induce the fibrosis in the interstitium.
That's point one.
Point number two is that
the fibrosis in the interstitium
in these disorders
is mediated by the macrophages.
Basically what happens
is these tiny particles come in,
they get to the bottom of the lung,
and in the very bottom of the lung,
the distal portion of the lung,
the only thing that you have
to defend yourself there
is the alveolar macrophage.
The alveolar macrophage consumes those particles,
and when it consumes them,
it says,
what the heck is this?
I don't recognize this as anything.
This is some foreign thing.
I have no idea what to do with this.
And so when it has no idea what to do with this,
it freaks out
and begins to start inducing fibrosis
all over the lung,
trying to basically wall off this garbage.
And as it induces this fibrosis,
that's what results
in the interstitial fibrosis
that you see in a pneumoconiosis.
And that's why I say
that the small particles have to,
they have to be able to induce fibrosis
by the macrophages.
Obviously they have to be small
because they wouldn't be able
to get to the bottom of the lung
if they weren't small,
and they have to be able
to induce fibrosis.
Now because this is going to be
a severe chronic disease,
there's going to need
to be a chronic exposure.
If you had a little bit of fibrosis
induced in a little area of the lung,
that wouldn't really create
clinical symptoms.
So chronic exposure
of some sort of occupational element,
which is a small particle,
which will then induce fibrosis,
which is going to be mediated
by the macrophages.
Those are the pneumoconiosis.
Now here are a few high yield ones,
and I put them in a table.
So the very first one
is called coal workers pneumoconiosis,
and you can refer to your book.
It might be a little hard to see
on the screen.
In coal workers pneumoconiosis,
the problem is carbon gets taken in
as they're working in coal mines,
for example,
and as this carbon comes in,
it gets into the macrophages,
and the macrophages don't recognize
what to do with it.
They begin to induce fibrosis,
and you get massive fibrosis
of the lung.
Now of course,
coal workers are chronically exposed
to this potentially.
So that results in massive fibrosis
of the lung,
and that is called
coal workers pneumoconiosis.
Now classically,
what that would result in
is something called black lung,
where the entire lung is black
due to the presence of this coal,
and it would result
in a shrunken lung
because the entire lung
becomes fibrotic.
One of the associations
with coal workers pneumoconiosis
is something called
rheumatoid arthritis,
which we'll talk about
when we do your joint lectures.
However,
the association of rheumatoid arthritis
with coal worker pneumoconiosis
is also known as Kaplan,
with a C,
Kaplan syndrome.
So that's an important
pathologic consideration.
Now let me remind you
that all of us
are exposed to carbon
just by breathing in
the pollution from the air
if you happen to be
in a big city.
And mild exposure
of carbon occurs constantly,
especially because
of that pollution.
If it's mild,
it doesn't really do anything.
It sort of builds up
in the macrophages,
and so when you have
buildup of carbon
within the macrophages,
that's called anthracosis,
and examiners like you
to know that.
So you can have anthracosis
within the macrophages
of the lung
and within the
hyalur lymph nodes.
Again, that is clinically
not significant,
but it is common
among the vast majority
of people
because the vast majority
of people are exposed
to pollutants
within the air.
All right?
So that's coal worker's
pneumoconiosis,
and I've also,
in this context,
explained anthracosis.
The next of the pneumoconiosis
is silicosis,
and in silicosis,
the idea is that
there's exposure to silica.
Now silica can occur
if the patient's
a silica minor.
It occurs, for example,
in sandblasters,
there's silica in sand,
and sandblasters
are people that take sand
and shoot it at brick
at a very, very high pressure
with the idea
that the friction created
by the shooting of sand
against brick
will actually clean the brick,
so it's a mechanism
used to clean
the surface of buildings,
and so a sandblaster,
quote-unquote,
could actually get exposed
to silica as well.
Now one important thing
about silica,
if you remember this,
you're done,
and that is that
when silica gets
into macrophages,
it impairs
the phagolysosomes
to form.
The phagosome
is the vesicle
that's generated
when macrophages
eat to kill something,
and the lysosome
is where the phagosome
merges in order
to be able
to destroy that thing.
So what happens
in this particular
situation of silicosis
is that the silica
gets into the macrophages
and impairs the formation
of the phagolysosomes.
Why is that important?
Because it's the only
pneumoconiosis,
and this is the
high-yield point.
It is the only
pneumoconiosis
that increases
your risk for TB.
Now, once you know
that it increases
your risk for TB,
then you're also
going to know
where it commonly
occurs within the lung,
and it results
in fibrotic nodules
usually in the upper
lobe of the lung.
So I use silicosis
and its relationship
with TB
to also remind me
that these patients
are going to have
fibrotic nodules
in the upper lobe
of the lung.
The next of the
pneumoconiosis
is beryllium,
and beryllium
can be seen in miners.
It can also be seen
in workers
in the aerospace industry.
Now, the idea
with beryllium
is that it results
in non-caseating granulomas
in the lung,
in the hyalur lymph nodes,
and in other parts
of the body,
in other systemic organs.
Now, guess what
that sounds like?
Non-caseating granulomas
in the lung,
in the hyalur lymph nodes,
and systemic organs.
Sounds exactly
like sarcoidosis,
and it is kind of
very similar
to sarcoidosis.
However,
in this particular case,
this is driven
by beryllium.
So this is what I call
the knee-jerk questions
on examinations,
where they give you
a classic history,
and you think
that this is just
sort of a slam-dunk question,
and so you quickly
pick sarcoidosis,
but actually they were
hinting at beryllium.
So if they tell you
that the patient
works for NASA
or recently designed
some sort of
stealth fighter
or something like that,
then that would be
a hint to you
that maybe they're
in the aerospace industry,
and so you want
to think twice
about beryllium.
Another important thing
about beryllium,
it increases the risk
for lung cancer.
But I would say
the highest yield
is that you get
these non-caseating
granulomas in the lung,
in the hyalur lymph nodes,
and in other organs.
The final pneumoconiosis
that we want to discuss
is asbestos.
Now asbestos fibers
would be seen
in people who are
classically construction workers.
It was used in construction
at one time.
Plumbers,
it was classically used
at one time
to insulate pipes
and shipyard workers
where there used
to be a classic exposure
as well.
Now in each of these cases,
the patient would get
exposed to asbestos fibers
and what's important
to know
is asbestos does
a couple things.
It creates fibrosis
in the lung
or fibrosis in the pleura
or cancer in the lung
or cancer in the pleura.
That's my little way
of remembering this.
Fibrosis of the lung,
fibrosis of the pleura,
cancer of the lung,
cancer of the pleura.
So if you get
cancer of the lung,
that's the standard
lung cancer
and it can also cause
cancer of the pleura
and remember that
is called mesothelioma.
Now there is a high yield
association
which I've already talked
about in your
neoplasia lectures
and that is patients
who are exposed
to asbestos
are much more likely
to get lung cancer,
much more likely
to get lung cancer
than they are
to get mesothelioma
and I've written that here
just to remind you
because it is so high yield.
When patients have
exposure to asbestos,
it requires a confirmation
and the way by which
we can make that confirmation
is we can pathologically
look for something
called asbestos bodies
and asbestos bodies
basically look like this.
You get this long
rod shaped particle
which classically
has little brown beads on it
and these little brown beads
they represent iron.
So there's iron
depositing on this rod
and this is also called
a ferruginous body
and so that's another name
for this particular particle
but essentially
this represents
asbestos within the patient
and so that's a pathologic way
by which we can confirm
the fact that the patient
is exposed to asbestos.
So those are the four
pneumoconiosis
and I've told you
what I think
to be the highest yield
for each of those
individual pneumoconiosis.
Sarcoidosis
is another disease
that can result
in granulomas
within the interstitium
of the lung
and those granulomas
would result
in restricted filling
of the lung.
Remember that sarcoidosis
is a systemic disease
characterized by
non-caseating granulomas
in multiple organs.
The most commonly
involved organs
would be the lung
and the hyalur lymph nodes
as I'll highlight momentarily.
Classically seen
in African American females
we don't know
what causes it.
It's probably
some unknown antigen
with a CD4 positive
helper T cell response.
Here's what the granulomas
look like.
Here I've illustrated
for you
this is the lung.
There's an airspace here
and then you've got
this pink region here
of epithelioid histiocytes.
Remember that the defining
cell of a granuloma
is an epithelioid histiocyte.
In addition
you have some
of the characteristic cells
for example
these giant cells.
So this is
the classic granuloma.
It's non-caseating
which means that
all of the cells
present within the granuloma
are alive.
There is no necrosis.
One of the characteristic
findings that can be seen
in the granulomas
of sarcoidosis
is something called
an asteroid body
and this is what we mean
by an asteroid body.
It's just a funny
configuration of some
of the giant cells
and it's one of the
characteristic findings
in sarcoidosis as well.
The granulomas
as I've said
they most commonly involve
the hyalur lymph node
in the lung.
Involvement of the lung
is going to then create
an interstitial problem
and that interstitial problem
will lead to a
restrictive lung disease.
Basically the lung
becomes less compliant
due to all of the
granulomas present
within the interstitium.
Of course the granulomas
can involve
multiple organs as well.
So if it involves the eye
you get uveitis.
If it involves the skin
you can get cutaneous nodules.
It can involve
the salivary glands
and the lacrimal glands
so it can mimic
Sjogren's syndrome
and this is very important
because again it's sort of
the knee jerk questions
that show up on exams.
They expect you to
expect you to jump
for Sjogren's syndrome
but actually
they're talking about
something different
and in this case
they're talking about
sarcoidosis.
So just remember
that it can involve
the salivary glands
and lacrimal glands
giving you the classic
doc I can't chew
a cracker
and there's dirt in my eyes
and an increased risk
of dental caries
those are the classic
clinical findings
in Sjogren's syndrome
and so you could actually
do a biopsy
and see non-caseating
granulomas
and if you have
non-caseating
granulomas
with those symptoms
that is sarcoidosis
that's classic
for sarcoidosis
I should say
and again
any tissue
can almost any tissue
can really be involved
I've just told you
a couple of the
high yield associations.
Now the way
that these patients
present is
the most common sign
is cough
but they can also
have shortness of breath
due to that
restrictive lung disease
that's going to be
created by the sarcoid.
Another very important
finding is
angiotensin converting
enzyme
can be elevated
in the blood
the patients have
hypercalcemia
this is important
I'd like to ask you
why.
So the hypercalcemia
occurs because
the granulomas
have one alpha
hydroxylase activity
and they can activate
vitamin D.
Now although we
classically apply this
to sarcoid
and say because
they're activating
vitamin D
there's going to be
hypercalcemia
in any disease
in which the patients
have a ton of
non-caseating granulomas
for example
there will be
excess activity
of the one alpha
hydroxylase
which will then
result in
the production
of hypercalcemia.
So for example
if a patient
was exposed to
beryllium
and developed
a very similar
picture to sarcoid
and they also have
hypercalcemia
that's okay
because it's
the non-caseating
granuloma
that actually has
the alpha one
hydroxylase activity
that's resulting
in that
hypercalcemia.
The treatment is steroids
but what's interesting
is that often
this disease
will resolve
spontaneously
without treatment.
The final
restrictive disease
is hypersensitivity
pneumonitis
and the idea
here is that
a patient
gets exposed
to some sort
of inhaled
organic antigen
it could be
for example
the feces
of a bird
or sometimes
feathers
etc.
and that results
in a granulomatous
reaction to that
antigen.
Now when there's
a granulomatous
reaction to that
antigen
the patients
will present
with fever
and cough
and shortness
of breath
usually hours
after the exposure
and this will
all resolve
if you remove
the exposure.
Now the initial
consequence
of being exposed
is that the patient
gets fever
cough
shortness of breath
and then they
move away
and they get
better.
However
if the patient
is constantly
exposed
then that would
result in
an interstitial
fibrosis
and that's why
we're talking
about it
in this particular
section
of your text.
that you get
a granulomatous
reaction
in the lung.
Now in this
case you're
going to get
a granulomatous
reaction
but what's
going to be
associated
with the
granulomatous
reaction
eosinophils.
Again it is
a hypersensitivity
pneumonitis
so classically
on the slide
you would see
granulomas
with eosinophils.
So that's
the end
of that section
and we're
going to move
on to
pulmonary hypertension
in the next
section.